Schwarzschild, Henry; Memorial Collection apap337
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection
1926-2013, Undated
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap337
2.0 cubic ft.
The Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection contains papers, journal articles and other written materials about the death penalty. Lansing, Michigan attorney and death penalty opponent Eugene G. Wanger donated this collection in memory of Henry Schwarzschild (1925-1996), longtime director of the American Civil Liberties Union's Capital Punishment Project, and head of the New York office of the National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty at the time of his death.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Eugene G. Wanger donated all the materials in this collection in 2013 to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Biographical Sketch
Lansing, Michigan attorney and death penalty opponent Eugene G. Wanger donated this collection in memory of Henry Schwarzschild (1925-1996), a civil rights advocate, longtime director of the American Civil Liberties Union's Capital Punishment Project, and head of the New York office of the National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty at the time of his death. Wanger, a delegate to Michigan's Constitutional Convention of 1961, authored the section of the state constitution which bans capital punishment. He also served on the board of the National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty and was a co-founder of the Michigan Committee Against Capital Punishment in 1972.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains papers, journal articles and other written materials about the death penalty. There are a number of topical articles written by Eugene G. Wanger, copies of Wanger's legislative testimony, illustrations, materials from death penalty abolitionist organizations, and photographs of Henry Schwarzschild.
More than 120 books and government documents also donated by Wanger were transferred to the book division of Special Collections to be catalogued. Please see the following annotated bibliography that Wanger created for the complete list:
Separated Materials
More than 120 books and government documents donated by Eugene G. Wanger were transferred to the book division of Special Collections. Please see the attached annotated bibliography.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized alphabetically. There are no series.
Death Penalty; Capital punishment--United States; Capital punishment--United States--History; Discrimination in capital punishment--United States; Death row--United States; Files by subject; Clippings; Political cartoons; journals (periodicals); Testimonies; Schwarzschild, Henry; Wanger, Eugene G.
- American Bar Association Evaluating Fairness and Accuracy in State Death Penalty Systems, 2006 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 1)
- American Bar Association Town Meeting, "The Crisis in Death Penalty Representation", 1996 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 3)
- American Journal of Orthopsychiatry with Special Section on Capital Punishment, 1975 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 4)
- The American Judicature Society, Undated (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 5)
- Bedau, Hugo Adam, "The Case Against the Death Penalty", 1973; 1977; 1984; 1992; ca. 1997 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 6)
- Bedau, Hugo Adam and Michael L. Radelet, "Miscarriages of Justice in Potentially Capital Cases", 1987 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 7)
- Bookman's Weekly, Special on Crime, Law and Mystery, 1990 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 8)
- Brochure to Boycott Florida Because of Death Penalty, Undated (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 9)
- Brooks, Rev. George W. Disarming the State's Lethal Weapon, 2002 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 10)
- Brown, Rev. S. "Capital Punishments, A Sermon Delivered in the Presbyterian Church, Zanesville. O.", 1997 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 11)
- Bureau of Justice Statistics Bulletin, 1993; 1996-1997 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 12)
- Campaign to End the Death Penalty, 2002 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 13)
- Canadian House of Commons Debates on Capital Punishment, 1987 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 14)
- Clippings About Capital Punishment, 1977; 1985; 1997; Undated (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 15)
- Congressional Bills About the Death Penalty, 1974; 1980 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 16)
- Congressional Record, 1974 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 17)
- Copies of Photographs of Henry Schwarzschild, 1987; 1994 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 18)
- Copy of Get Well Card Sent to Schwarzschild from Participants in Cooley Law School Symposium, 1996 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 19)
- "A Culture of Life and the Penalty of Death," A Statement of the United State Conference of Catholic Bishops, 2005 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 20)
- Cushing, Robert Renny and Susan Sheffer Dignity Denied: The Experiences of Murder Victims' Family Members Who Oppose the Death Penalty, 2002 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 21)
- Death Penalty and Related Issues, A Selected Bibliography, Undated (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 22)
- Death Penalty Focus, 2001; 2010 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 23)
- Death Penalty Information Center, 1993-1994 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 24)
- Death Penalty Information Center, 1997-1999; 2002; 2005; 2009 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 25)
- Death Penalty Information Center, "Understanding Capital Punishment", 2003 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 26)
- "The Death Penalty: The Religious Community Calls for Abolition", 1988 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 27)
- Department of Criminal Justice, California State University, Long Beach, "Death Penalty Issues,"Journal of Contemporary Criminal Justice, 1989 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 28)
- Don't Kill for Me Postcard, Used by Canadian Anti-Death Penalty Supporters, ca. 1987 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 29)
- Duncan, Rev. James, "A Discourse Upon War, and Capital Punishments", 1997 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 30)
- Equal Justice USA, 2000 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 31)
- Fact Sheets About Capital Punishment, Undated (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 32)
- Fagal, William Three Hours to Live, 1967 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 33)
- General Writings About the Death Penalty by Eugene G. Wanger, 1975; 1997; 2002; 2009 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 34)
- Gunterman, Joe and Trevor Thomas This Life We Take: A Case Against the Death Penalty, 1987 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 35)
- Holmes, Kirby, "Michigan Should Reinstate the Death Penalty for First Degree Murder", 1978 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 36)
- Lighting the Torch of Conscience, Undated (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 37)
- Lincoln, James H. "The Everlasting Controversy: Michigan and the Death Penalty", 1987 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 38)
- Materials About Efforts to Stop Execution of William R. Jones, Missouri, 2002 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 39)
- Michigan and the Death Penalty, 1974-2004; Undated (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 40)
- Michigan and the Death Penalty, Articles and Op-Ed by Eugene G. Wanger, 1974; 1993; 2002 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 41)
- Moratorium 2000, 1998; Undated (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 42)
- Murder Victims' Families for Human Rights, 2006-2011 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 43)
- National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty The Abolitionist's Directory, 1985; 1987; 1990; 1992 (Box 1 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 44)
- National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty, General Organizing Materials, 1990-1992; 1995; 1997; Undated (Box 2 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 1)
- National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty Lifelines, 1997; 2002; 2009-2011 (Box 2 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 2)
- National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty, National Conferences, 1981; 1988-1991; 1995-1996; 2001-2002 (Box 2 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 3)
- National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty, National Conferences, 2003-2005; 2009-2011 (Box 2 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 4)
- National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty, Regional Conferences, 1986; 1992 (Box 2 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 5)
- "National Council on Crime and Delinquency, "Capital Punishment in the United States,"Crime & Delinquency, 1980 (Box 2 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 6)
- Oklahoma Execution Moratorium Petition, ca. 2000 (Box 2 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 7)
- Olivera, Nancy, "Writing Wrongs: How to Shift Public Opinion on the Death Penalty with Letters to the Editor, 2009-2010 (Box 2 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 8)
- People of Faith Against the Death Penalty, 1999 (Box 2 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 9)
- Postcards Depicting Death Penalty Related Images, 1987-1997; Undated (Box 2 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 10)
- Quaife, M. M., "Capital Punishment in New York", 1926 (Box 2 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 11)
- Radzinowica, Leon, "Sir James Fitzjames Stephen", 1957 (Box 2 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 12)
- Rally to Stop the Death Penalty Outside the U.S. Supreme Court, 1996 (Box 2 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 13)
- Report of the Standing Committee on the Judiciary on the Subject of Abolishing Capital Punishment, 1997 (Box 2 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 14)
- Robbins, Tim Dead Man Walking, 2005 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 1)
- Satirical Pictures, Undated (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 2)
- The Southern Center for Human Rights, Frederick Douglass Awards Dinner, 2002 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 3)
- Streib, Victor, "Death Penalty for Juveniles", 1985 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 4)
- Streib, Victor, "The Juvenile Death Penalty Today", 1991 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 5)
- Strouse, Evelyn, "The Death Penalty: Issues in the Debate," Public Affairs Pamphlet No. 648, 1987 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 6)
- Testimony of Eugene G. Wanger About Capital Punishment, 1975; 1994; 1999; 2004-2005 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 7)
- Thomas, Trevor This Life We Take, 1970 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 8)
- Twelve Angry Jurors, A Review and a Comment, 2000 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 9)
- Uniform Crime Reports for the United States, 1972 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 10)
- Van Ness, Daniel W. "A Call to Dialogue on Capital Punishment", 1985 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 11)
- Virginians for Alternatives to the Death Penalty, 2002 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 12)
- Wanger, Eugene G. "Historical Reflections on Michigan's Abolition on the Death Penalty,"Thomas M. Cooley Law Review, 1996 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 13)
- Wanger, Eugene G. "Legislative Testimony Against Capital Punishment, 1962-2005, Together with Information Leaflets and Several Other Anti-Death penalty Writings", 2013 (Oversized 1)
- Wanger, Eugene G., ed. "Letters on the Penalty of Death", 1975 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 14)
- Wanger, Eugene G., "National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty: A 30th Anniversary History", 2006 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 15)
- Wanger, Eugene G. Reasons for Reviving Capital Punishment in Michigan and Why They Are Wrong, 1989 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 16)
- Wanger, Eugene G., Satirical Pictures, 1989; Undated (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 17)
- Wanger, Eugene G., "Why We Should Reject Capital Punishment", 1978 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 18)
- Washington Research Project, "The Case Against Capital Punishment", 1971 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 19)
- Weekly World News Photographs of Ted Bundy Following His Execution, 1989 (Oversized 1)
- The Western Missouri Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty, 2002 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 20)
- Whitman, Claudia and Lawson Strickland Capital Defense Handbook for Defendants and Their Families, 2005 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 21)
- Why Kill People Who Kill People to Show that Killing People is Wrong?, 1985 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 22)
- World Coalition Against the Death Penalty (1-2 of 3), 2009-2012 (Box 3 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 23-24)
- World Coalition Against the Death Penalty (3 of 3), 2009-2012 (Box 4 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 1)
- Zehr, Howard, "Death as a Penalty: A Biblical Perspective", 1990 (Box 4 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 2)
- Zehr, Howard, "Death as a Penalty: A Moral, Practical and Theological Discussion", Undated (Box 4 (Henry Schwarzschild Memorial Collection ), Folder 3)